我父母没什么特别的
也并没有经历过戏剧化的事
没离过婚
但这就是我父母
我想画一本画集来缅怀他们
说来奇怪 一本写我父母的书
和其他足球界英雄和烹饪书籍相比竟然成了畅销书
我想 父母也一定很骄傲吧
也有可能很尴尬
他们可能会说 事情才不是这样的
或者说 你怎么能这么说
这个 反正我就这样说了
这就是他们的故事
And this is their story.
伦敦
1928年
- 再见 妈    - 再见
- 早啊 厄恩 伙计    - 早
早
星期一
打扫快点 艾瑟尔
还要点炉子和铺床呢
知道了 夫人 马上就好
艾瑟尔 弄完没有
马上 夫人
对不起 夫人
星期二
嘿 嘿
星期三
艾瑟尔 你在哪
这就来 夫人
星期四
艾瑟尔
- 艾瑟尔  - 哦
来了 来了
星期五
哎
你好 姑娘
噢 是你啊
我想自我介绍一下
你已经对我抖抹布好多次了
不不不 我不是故意的 只是
我叫厄尼斯特
- 我叫艾瑟尔  - 好名字
呃 艾瑟尔 可以和我一起照张相吗
这个 我
我还有很多活没干完
- 你几点下班    - 大概7点
- 好 当地要上映《侩子手之家》
- 你是说加冕礼    - 没错
- 八点开始 我们到时候见   - 谢谢 那就
- 那就太好了  - 一言为定
这些 是给你的
真好看
- 到时候见   - 好
我一定会去的
噢
厄尼斯特
刽子手之家
主演
维克托·麦克拉格伦
两张票 谢谢
- 维克托·麦克拉格伦     - 是谁
- 就是上面那个人   - 哦
我最喜欢的演员
哦
噢 厄尼斯特 这音乐多美妙啊
天呐
要花5先令才能进
要我说太奢侈了
这样吧 教堂大厅里只要1先令不到
{\fs14\bord2\shad0\3a&H32&\3c&H1B1B1B&
就在下周六
- 来不来 - 噢 厄尼斯特
- 好美的花啊 亲爱的   - 这是我爸种的 他对这花园可上心了
- 你们都是在这里长大的?   - 对 我们11个
鲍勃 毕提 麦格 艾迪 我 弗兰克 弗娄 杰西 乔治 乔和比尔
老天 真不少
来见见我爸妈吧
厄尼斯特 你的领带
- 要留个好印象   - 噢 好 亲爱的
乔治死在了战场上
鲍勃从小夭折 毕提只活到两岁半
- 真可怜  - 嗯
你好啊 女儿
妈 这是厄尼斯特
很高兴认识你 呃 保雅夫人
你还没请我去你家呢
这个 我家没你家好
什么意思 没我家好
呃 有个费钢厂 还有收破烂的
外面到处都有打架的 女的也打
警察都不敢去那儿
上次有个警察去了 被痛打一顿
他们坐在警察身上吹哨子来叫更多的警察来打
噢 厄尼斯特
那里不适合你 亲爱的
我没理解错的话 你是想离开这里?
是的 夫人
去结婚
是 夫人
嫁给一个男人?
是的 夫人
那
希望你不会后悔
对不住了 夫人
箱子给我吧 亲爱的
噢
我也不想离开她们 她们很无助
她们什么也不会做
你服侍得她们够好了
...资本主义
别说脏话 厄尼斯特
怎么了
不用担心她们 很快就会有新的女仆的
我不是个女仆
我是陪嫁过来的 还有
我马上就要结婚了
我也是
真漂亮
可是825英镑 我们付得起
那么多吗
没事的 很快我的工资就会是一周三几尼
几尼: 1663年英国发行的一种金币,=21先令,于1813年停止流通
另外我们有三十年的时间 19...55年 这就是我们的了
锻铁篱笆门 小姐
别出洋相了
看呐 厄尼斯特 大理石柱
看看
噢
噢 厄尼斯特 空间真大
- 我们可以装上电灯   - 对 好看又时尚
弗艾德兄弟有个收音机 能听德语电台
听德语干嘛
噢 法式窗户
噢 厄尼斯特 还有浴室
对 还有抽水马桶
过来 厄尼斯特
嗯
哈
卧室好大 一个房间就有四个窗户
光窗帘就得花好多钱
和家的感觉有点不一样 是吧 亲爱的
对两个人来说有点太大了
也许有天会不只我们两个
- 你是说房客?    - 不是
这里可以作为婴儿房
在厨房上面 漂亮又暖和
把这些老古董都弄出去吧
哈 这炉子一定是避难所里的
你好啊 小猫咪
- 噢 - 一小片美丽的花园
多有乡土气息啊
噢 我一直想要个属于我自己的花园
一个小自行车棚和工作间
记住 别弄很大
我们还没结婚你就发号施令起来了
厄尼斯特 我真不敢相信
- 我们有厨房和存放室  - 还有起居室和餐厅
- 一个花园还有一个车棚   - 别忘了走廊
还有浴室 真豪华
噢
对 就这样 拿好了
没错 很好 布瑞执夫人 很好
现在 别动 笑一个
再来一张
上啊 厄恩 亲一个 来啊
对 再来一个 再来一个 所有人
这卧室也太大了
得在床底下放个装衣服的箱子
那叫衣柜 厄尼斯特
噢 对 对 没错
早啊 夫人 今天怎么样
我刚擦干净 别踩 年轻人
噢
噢 厄尼斯特
转了一圈又回来了
真不错
12点钟应该就能送完 到时我就收拾那些老古董
真想看看它背面是什么样
是铁块 亲爱的
那些新式气灶 才是我想要的
小心点 厄尼斯特
喔吼
旧铁块 旧铁块
你在找肉 想做顿大餐
厄尼斯特 别唱那首伦敦老歌了
穿着时尚 崭新礼帽
打上你父亲的绿色领带
可我不会给你的表和链两便士
旧铁块 旧铁块
好了
嘿
噢
这样应该行了
真好 这床质量真好
几乎是全新的 应该是红木的
唔
弹簧不错 新婚夫妇就得要好的弹簧
快来试试 亲爱的
才不呢 厄尼斯特
大白天的
- 排水板弄好了 亲爱的   - 真不错
正好嵌在角落里 还能拆下来清洗
有了它还有新的灶台
字幕
看 装好了
呃 报上说超过两百万人失业了
我做个送奶员真幸运 艾特
我讨厌楼梯下面的煤
煤灰到处都是 太劣质了
哈 我在花园那用砖搭个煤库好了
那就太好了
怎么样 艾特 吼吼吼
噢 厄尼斯特 这也太大了
我来做几个宽松的毯子
这是高档旅馆里的物件 捡大便宜了
水箱下面我做了个帘子可以挡住管道
我的外衣放在那 管道很快就会烘干
可 那样你的外套就会像臭牛奶味
是啊 那还是别了
你觉得你还会升职吗
恐怕不会 我才不想
就像领班那样 整天憋在满是罐子的房间里 算来算去
为了能看到小鸟我也不会干 我喜欢呼吸新鲜空气
我本来可以嫁给...
一个深海潜水员
- 那你怎么没嫁?   - 因为
我不爱他
两年后
为什么把一张孩子的照片放在床头
你觉得呢
这也不是我们亲戚啊
我们结婚都两年多了
我马上就37岁了
噢
别哭啊
对不起
噢 别哭了 别哭了
我知道 我都知道
晚报 晚报
希特勒在德国掌权
- 给 理查德    - 你好啊 厄恩
- 晚报   - 不好  - 希特勒掌权
希特勒 这家伙
说要在这儿发行他的书
叫《我的奋斗》  - 噢
这人还真不错
哈?
艾特
- 给你个惊喜 亲爱的   - 噢
- 新镜子   - 真好看
你怎么拿来的
- 我放在车上推着来的   - 多少钱
半块钱 我从乡下的吉普赛人那里买的
我也有个惊喜给你
- 是吗 - 我去看了...
呃 医生
哦 然后呢
- 你是说  - 嗯
- 我们   - 对
我们要...
耶
- 简直不敢相信   - 噢 艾特
- 生日快乐 亲爱的   - 噢 厄尼斯特
你的贺卡 一年比一年大 今年的还鼓起来了
而最好的礼物要到明年一月才会来
- 再来点茶 艾特   - 好
加把劲 布瑞执夫人
很好
老天呐 大惊小怪
邻居都被你叫醒了
天呐 艾特
等等
站住 布瑞执先生
不准带着瓶子进产房
不好意思 女士...夫人...护士
- 她还好...    - 是个男孩
- 她还...   孕妇平安
谢天谢地
尽量多休息 布瑞执夫人
宝宝很好
谢谢你 医生
你好 医生
艾特
噢 厄尼斯特
噢
- 什么时候出生的   - 5点左右
我刚送完亚石兰街
几乎跑完了
感觉怎么样 你看起来很疲惫
很累
它浑身通红
他 是他
噢 对
布瑞执先生 借一步说话
好的 医生
- 这次真是千钧一发  - 噢
你妻子已经38岁了
以后最好别再要孩子了
但我们想要一个真正的家庭
想要孩子 就没有妻子
对不起
晚安
往右坐点 艾特 我可不想把尿布也拍上
好了
别动
我还没说你就笑上了
国会正在讨论工人阶级的公寓里该不该
建浴室 工人阶级参议员 当然
他们总是说就算建个浴室
也会被用来放煤
是吗 我怎么没发现我们浴室里有很多煤
厄尼斯特 我们又不是工人阶级
哈
是你啊
- 嗨 艾特 我来看看宝宝   - 嗯
进来吧
你怎么样
厄尼斯特 你继母...
又来了
嗨 妈
我带来了几个厚实的瓶子
还有一点煤
噢 谢谢
谢了 妈 不必拿东西来的
我的小宝贝在哪
N
长那么大了
这里是伦敦BBC广播电台...
- 什么  - 接下来是新闻时间
德国总理希特勒宣布....
犹太人不再属于德国公民的最新法律今日实行
厄恩 把那天杀的无线电关了
我可不想让里面的人听见我说的话
首相大臣说
新的会面将会...
艾特 你知道如果你是个身在德国的犹太人
就不能嫁给德国人吗
嗯?
我才不想嫁给德国人
不是这个意思
这可真是个好东西
只要按下按钮再搅一下
BBC今年晚些时候
就要开电视频道了
那是什么东西
呃 看起来像是能看见图画的收音机
移动的图片
在说话?
对
以后就会在家看图片而不是到外面看了
什么 就坐着看就行?
- 对   - 嗯
恐怕只有上流人士才能看
噢
让我看看尿布
又该洗了
报道说一户人家每周要花6英镑
才算脱离贫困水平
- 贫困水平是什么    - 不知道
我只是希望我能一周赚6英镑
现在孩子身体长那么快
唔
嘿嘿 这样才对 儿子
再来 再来
噢 厄尼斯特 他真长成大孩子了
- 不 他和我一样瘦    - 是结实 厄尼斯特
很高 头发也好看
看看这些卷
看 这是新的
包厢里还有茶喝
还有戴帽子穿围裙的服务员
真奢侈啊
- 唔   - 下次再来吧 亲爱的   - 再来一次
好吧 下次
怎么了 亲爱的
怎么哭了
- 我做完了   - 什么 什么
- 他的头发   - 呃
头发都被剪了 那好看的卷发
早晚也得剪 艾特
总不能让他一辈子都顶着个少女头吧
他也不小了 马上就要上学了
我知道
你好啊 儿子
我妈怎么了
妈 妈
雷蒙德 你不该在学校吗
妈 妈 啊
你怎么回来了
上课期间不能回家的
你穿过大路过来的
一定是这样
- 我找不着马桶   - 你找不到...
我们不是带你去过吗
不是 那是女生厕所 女生才那样
- 不 男生有时也要那样  - 不是
全是女生厕所 我要上大号
你好啊 伯尼特太太
是啊 天气真好 布瑞执太太
看来希特勒有敌对行动 理由还很充分
Sounds like that Hitler's on the warpath, good and proper.
噢
静观其变
一群疯子
乔治就是死在上次战争里的
还有汤姆兄弟
感觉也没过多少时间啊
我们可怜的的老妈妈一直也没走出这个阴影
电视台会在每天晚上播出一个半小时
真可怕
岂不是要每天都要看图片
天呐 这里有张温莎公爵及公爵夫人
同希特勒握手的图片
噢 那这人还不算坏啊
什么
看 妈
首相今天从德国回来
并在机场向人们
表示了和平
我和德国总理希特勒又进行了一次谈话
这就是我们两人签署的文件
天呐 艾特 首相把半个捷克斯洛伐克都给了希特勒
是吗
他说这是很荣幸的和平之举
好好想想 你要不要吃点烤面包 厄尼斯特
不想吃
晚报
你好啊 厄恩
你在家吗 艾特
在
希特勒抵达布拉格了
布拉格: 前捷克斯洛伐克首都
很快就会来我们这儿
希特勒 来温布尔顿花园
报上说政府要花20万英镑
来修筑防空洞
我们最好准备好
噢 别放在桌子上 厄尼斯特
打上封网显得好古板 厄尼斯特
那也没防毒气房间古板
毒气?
- 噢 我还真没想到  - 我们得塞住烟囱
把门窗上的缺口都用胶带封上
地板之间还得用湿报纸盖上
希特勒可是个老混蛋
挼
雷蒙德 老实点
这不是游戏 知道吗
栗子树下
管家对我说
你想要防毒面具更合适
加入闪亮的军团
多看几遍 直到全都记在心里
噢 真希望能有个合适的防毒面具包
湿透的纸盒加根线 不公平
噢 亲爱的
厄尼斯特 厄尼斯特 听得到吗
- 听不见   - 我能听见
小声点 儿子
你相信吗 爱尔兰炸弹落到了伦敦、曼彻斯特和伯明翰
什么时候结束啊
这些爱尔兰人 就像该死的的阿拉伯人和犹太人一样
- 总是这样   - 还有塞尔维亚人和克罗地亚人
都一样坏  还有印度人和穆斯林
他们怎么就不能像我们一样和平相处呢
现在插播一条新闻
这是首相的发言
我在内阁向你们宣布
在那栗子树下
- 嘘 是首相  - 首相对我说
嘘 儿子
...给德国的最后通牒
声明11点前没有回复的话
那就准备撤回
在波兰的驻兵吧
因为我们即将开战
我必须要告诉你们这样的要求历史上还没有被接受过
因此 我们将与德国开战
老天
真要开战了
妈?
政府今天宣布
国内150万儿童将会撤离
住在大城镇里的孩子...
- 不   - ...要暂时搬离自己的家...
- 不 他们不能带走我的儿子    - 当然要带走
不行 除非跨过我的尸体
或我儿子的尸体
- 你真想这样吗   - 噢
- 噢  厄尼斯特   - 不让他走他就会死 他必须得走
对不起 亲爱的 来吧
别哭
别哭 我的爱人
我都知道
你要好好的 雷蒙德
上来吧
上来 儿子 就到这里了
再见 儿子
- 我们会给你寄东西的   - 请离开站台
我知道 我知道
再见 儿子 再见
再见 儿子
他走了
- 他走了   - 别哭了 亲爱的
他在乡下更安全
可他才5岁啊
厄尼斯特
厄尼斯特 这一定是雷蒙德的信
真的是
亲爱的爸爸妈妈 弗娄阿姨和贝蒂阿姨对我很好
看 他还画了张画
我睡在弗娄阿姨卧室里的一个折叠床上
噢 可怜的家伙
我喝装在桶里的牛奶 不装在瓶子里是因为现挤的
牛奶不放瓶子里?真没见过
有了干草 就能坐在拉货的马背上
我差点就颠吐了
此致敬礼 雷蒙德
此致敬礼
当心我种的金鱼草 厄尼斯特
你会做吗
当然会 等着瞧吧
好了 完工
就这吗?这就完了?
真能防炮弹吗
等着瞧吧
苏联入侵芬兰了
我还以为要入侵波兰
- 是啊   - 但他们说波兰是德国入侵的
- 没错  - 那又是谁入侵了捷克斯洛伐克   - 德国
德国总是侵略别国
- 希望有天他们会侵略苏联    - 这个 不大可能
- 他们是联盟   - 让苏联侵略德国也好   - 别傻了
要是他们互相侵略
还是会波及其他国家
艾特 你根本不懂政治
你看
该死的避难所
你觉得他们会打到我们这个街道吗
没事的
据说希特勒保证荷兰和比利时是友国
那还可以
怎么样 还行吧
我还以为消防员会有带流苏的铜帽
要穿成那样早就被处决了
终于
丘吉尔接任了
- 血汗和泪水    - 厄尼斯特
- 别恶心我了    - 这是上流人士说的 又不是我
这是没错 但这也是说给普通人听的
他在家里也这样说话?
威刚德将军声称法国之战已经结束
英国之战即将开始
战争取决于
基督教徒的存亡
但战争的狂怒
将转向我们
希特勒知道他要么击垮我们
要么被打败
我们要站起来反抗
整个欧洲都会解放
世界人民将走向阳光普照的高地
如果我们失败了
那么全世界 包括美国
将会陷入黑暗时代的深渊
因此让我们承担起自己的责任
'Let us therefore brace ourselves to our duties,
要相信 大英联邦
'so bear ourselves that if the British Empire and its Commonwealths
能延续一千年
'last for 1,000 years,
人们会说
'men will still say...
这是他们最好的时刻
'..this was their finest hour.'
宽广的 阳光普照的高地
"Broad, sunlit uplands."
说得好 最好的时刻
Good old Winston! Our finest hour!
他们把我们家的铁门和栏杆都拆走了
They're starting to take away our nice gate and railings.
- 我会再做一个木门   - 好可惜
- I'll make a wooden gate. - Oh, it's a shame.
他们连平底锅也要
They want saucepans too.
他们用来造喷火式战斗机
They make 'em into Spitfires.
想想我们的前门成了战斗机也是好笑
Funny to think of our front gate being a Spitfire.
前门跑到了楼梯上
Front door's halfway up the stairs.
我的窗帘都给糟蹋了
It's spoiled my loose covers.
已经不错了
Could've been worse, Ette.
我们不是逃出来了嘛
We got off light.
我只是高兴雷蒙德不用经历这些
I'm glad Raymond was well clear of all this.
也许等我们清理完
Perhaps when we've got this mess cleared up
就可以去多塞特去看看儿子
we could take a trip down to Dorset and give him a visit.
妈 爸 看看我
Mum! Dad! Look at me!
看
Look!
雷蒙德 小心点 亲爱的
Raymond, be careful, dear.
不用担心 艾特 他已经习惯了
No need to worry about him, Ethel. He's got quite used to things now.
美好的乡村味道 是吧 小子
Oh! Lovely country smells, eh, boysie?
- 猪长成这样是不是因为灯火管制    - 噢 艾特
- Are the pigs like that because of the blackout? - Oh, Ette.
噢
- PIG GRUNTS - Ooh!
走吧 雷蒙德 我们已经看过猪了
Come along, Raymond. We've seen the pigs.
他在学校还好吧 弗娄
He's fitted into the school very well, hasn't he, Flo?
- 他就跟从小就在这里似的  - 那就好
- It's as if he's always been here. - Oh, good...
妈 学校里的孩子都有靴子
Mum, the boys at school all have boots.
他们也是一般的孩子 艾瑟尔 来自兰贝斯和巴尔明迪
They're common boys, Ethel, from Lambeth and Bermondsey.
能不能给我买双靴子
Can I have boots?
当然不行 雷蒙德
Certainly not, Raymond.
我一直想要个乡下小屋
I've always dreamed of a cottage in the country.
不敢相信外面还在打仗
Down here it's hard to believe there's a war on.
来吧 小猪
Come on, piggies.
莫里森牌的假避难所
That Mr Morrison and his soppy shelter's ruined
把我的餐厅都给毁了
my nice dining room.
政府预警 亲爱的
Government precautions, dear.
至少我们不用睡大街
Still, at least we won't have to go out into the cold.
你看起来跟关在动物园笼子里似的
- ETHEL LAUGHS - You look like you're in the zoo.
我会把它涂成褐色来配家具
I'll paint it brown to tone in with the furniture.
柔褐色 厄尼斯特
A nice pastel brown, Ernest.
老天
Blimey.
什么
What?
德国侵略苏联了
Germany's invaded Russia!
当时就应该跟你打个6便士的赌
I wish I'd betted you sixpence.
晚安 亲爱的
Night, dear.
晚安
Night.
厄尼斯特 你拿尺子在干吗
Ernest, what on earth are you doing with that ruler?
量5吋 只要放5吋水就够了
Marking five inches. You're only allowed five inches of water.
要是你很胖 水自己就上来了
But if you were fat, it would be higher up.
白金汉宫的国王都是这样做的
Yeah, well, the King's done it at Buckingham Palace.
不公平 胖子一用水就变深了
It's not fair, fat people getting a deeper bath.
所以说不要一个人洗啊
They say you're supposed to share the bath too, darling.
不正经
Disgusting!
- 我们一起洗   - 但不能同时
- We share ours. - But not at the same time.
这里 来 快点
Over here! Go on, go on!
杰瑞会被砸的
Jerry's got a direct hit.
那栋建筑要倒了
Those buildings are going to topple.
- 里面有没有人   - 不知道 希望没有
- Is there anyone in 'em? - Don't know. Hope to God not.
- 泰德    - 这里 厄恩 左边
- Ted! - Over here, Ern! On the left. That!
- 快 左窗口   - 快
- Go on, left window. - Come on!
左
Left.
小心
Watch out!
终于回来了
Oh, at last.
你没事吧
Are you all right?
太累了
Tired.
一直在码头
Been in the docks.
整整14个小时
14 hours.
来 我给你把靴子脱了
Here. Let me get your boots off.
- 好了    - 死了很多人
- There. - Loads of dead.
小孩子
Little kiddie.
都被砸成了碎块
All in bits.
我得
I had to...
好了 好了
There, there.
大哭一场吧
Have a good cry.
老天 白金汉宫报告 生病补偿 失业补偿
Cor! This Beveridge report! Sickness pay, unemployment pay,
养老金 儿童福利
old age pensions, kiddies welfare,
免费医疗
free medicines, free hospitals.
别念了 厄尼斯特 快来帮忙
Don't read, Ernest. Help!
从出生到死去都有社会福利
Social security from the cradle to the grave.
真正的福利国家
The welfare state.
这正是工人奋斗的目标 我们成功了
It's what the workers have always fought for. We've won!
-不还是有代价  - 当然有
- It will have to be paid for. - Course it will.
全力前进 这才是重点
We all chip in, that's the whole idea.
没工作 病了 又或者是退休了 还怎么前进
You can't chip in if you're out of work, or off sick, or on a pension.
这个
No, well...
当然不能 一定会解决的
Course not. It's all got to be worked out.
这是经济问题 经济上会实现的
It's economics, see? Economics will see to it.
好了
There.
完成
All done.
噢 厄尼斯特
Oh, Ernest.
我知道 我都知道
I know. I know.
- 弗娄阿姨   - 怎么了
- Auntie Flo. - Yes, dear?
嗯 我想我自己的床了
Mm... I wish I could sleep in my own bed again.
你当然会想 希特勒就要被打跑了 雷蒙德
Course you do, dear. That Mr Hitler's on the run now, Raymond.
我保证你很快就会回伦敦了
I'm sure you'll be back in London soon enough.
好了
There. All done.
你在吗
You there?!
- 怎么了 艾特   - 亲爱的 我升职了
- What's up, Ette? - Dearest, I've been promoted.
- 乙等职员   - 真好
- Clerk, grade B3. - Cor!
再也不用在腐烂的冰冷仓库里打包了
No more packing parcels in that rotten freezing warehouse?
没错 我要进办公室工作了
No, I'm going to work in an office.
我还有个好消息 艾特
And that's not all, Ette.
看 这是儿子的信
Look, a letter from our boy.
估计儿子现在就能回家了
They reckon he can come home now.
噢 噢 厄尼斯特
Oh! Oh, Ernest!
没错 儿子
That's it, son.
挖 挖 挖 让你的肌肉变强壮
# Dig, dig, dig Feel your muscles getting big
继续挥铁锹
# Keep on pushing in the spade
大头菜 土豆和萝卜
# The turnip tops The potatoes and the carrots
没有你的劳作就不会发芽
# Cannot sprout without your aid
别管虫子
BOTH: # Don't mind the worms
别管它们蠕动
# Just ignore the squirms
腰酸背疼就快乐地唱歌
# When your back aches Laugh with glee!
继续挖 直到把敌人激怒
# And keep on digging till we give our foes a wigging
挖 挖 挖向胜利
# Dig, dig, dig to victory! #
- 来口茶吧 儿子   - 谢了 爸
- Cup of tea, boysie? - Thanks, Dad.
乡下的空气还真适合你
That country air has got you fit.
爸
Dad?
快来 儿子
Come on, son!
- 去避难所 快跑    - 找掩护
- Down the shelter! Run! - Take cover!
飞弹
Doodlebug!
卧倒 儿子 卧倒
Get down, son! Get down!
引擎关掉了
Engine's cut out.
老天 要落下来了
Christ, it's coming down!
好险
Cor. That was close.
- 我还真不知道这下面是亮蓝色 爸    - 快起来 儿子
- I didn't know they were bright blue underneath, Dad. - Come on, son.
避难所 免得来更多炸弹
Shelter. Before any more of the blighters come over.
明天还是把你送到乡下去吧
We'd better get you back down the country tomorrow.
哎呀 听起来今晚也不太平
Crikey, dear. Sounds like a lot got through tonight.
我什么也听不见
I can't hear anything.
抱紧 亲爱的
Hold tight, duck.
什么避难所 全都是碎玻璃
Some shelter. Full of glass.
莫里森牌避难所 那莫里森也一定是个卑鄙的家伙
Morrison shelters. That Mr Morrison must be a proper twerp.
还好儿子没在里面
Good job the boy wasn't in it.
他才走了两天
He's only been gone two days.
桃乐茜 珀金斯还在绽放
The old Dorothy Perkins is still in bloom.
她幸存了下来
She survived.
可怜他连泰迪熊都没带上
Pity he didn't take his teddy with him.
噢 厄尼斯特
Oh, Ernest.
还会有多少像这样的泰迪熊呢
How much more of this is there going to be?
- 厄尼斯特  - 怎么了  - 小心点 这是你喝的第二杯了
- Ernest? - What? - Careful, that's your second glass of beer.
- 欧洲胜利了 艾特   - 没错
- Victory in Europe, Ette! - Yeah! - CHEERING
不管什么时候走在兰贝斯的街道    - 看 快看我爸
- # Any time you're Lambeth way... # - Look! Look at Dad!
不论白天晚上
# Any evening, any day
你会发现
# You'll find us all
走着兰贝斯步伐
# Doing the Lambeth walk, oi!
每个兰贝斯的小姑娘
# Every little Lambeth gal
和兰贝斯的小伙子
# With her little Lambeth pal
你都能看见
# You'll find 'em all
走着兰贝斯步伐
# Doing the Lambeth walk, oi!
一切都免费易得
# Everything's free and easy
想怎么样就怎么样
# Do as you darn well pleasey
你怎么不一起来
# Why don't you make your way there? Go there, stay there! #
来吧 阿瑟 这是胜利的日子
Come on, Arthur! It's VE Day!
高兴点 你看起来就像是丢了尾巴的狗
Cheer up. You look like a dog that's lost its tail!
我儿子死了
I lost my boy.
噢 是啊
Oh, yeah...
对不起 伙计
I'm sorry, mate.
对不起 我忘了
I'm sorry, I forgot.
对不起
Sorry.
天 想想 再也不会有战争了
Cor. Just think, there'll never be another war.
杰西的儿子还在打日本人 别忘了
Jessie's Bob is still fighting the Japs, don't forget.
现在可以把这东西拆了
And you can knock this thing down.
不过得等我收拾好
When I finish tidying it.
看 发芽了
Look. It's come up.
- 这是什么 儿子    - 梨树
- What's that, son? - A pear tree.
弗娄阿姨从吃过的梨里给了我些种子
Auntie Flo gave me the pips from a pear we ate.
最好别长太大 要不就挡光线了
Better not get too big, it will block out all the light.
别说丧气话 厄尼斯特
Don't discourage the boy, Ernest.
我倒是挺喜欢梨树的
I like a nice pear.
亲爱的
Darling!
工人阶级胜利了
Labour's won!
成功了
We're in! ERNEST LAUGHS
丘吉尔真丢人
Such a shame for poor Mr Churchill.
工人没事了 终于胜利了
The working man will be all right now. At last!
他还救了我们家的咸猪肉呢
He saved our bacon in the war.
- 真他妈不可思议   - 厄尼斯特
- Bloody marvellous. - Ernest!
丘吉尔就不说脏话 人家是个绅士
Mr Churchill never swears. He's a gentleman.
- 我也是工人阶级 妈   - 嘘 儿子
- I'm Labour, Mum. - Shush, dear.
据悉
- NEWSREADER: - 'It is now estimated
落在广岛的原子弹
'that casualties from the atomic bomb
造成的死亡人数在十万以上
'dropped on the city of Hiroshima could exceed 100,000 dead.'
一颗炸弹就死十万人
100,000 dead from one bomb.
至少战争算是停了
Well, at least it will put paid to wars.
- 呃 为什么   - 有这样的炸弹还怎么打
- Eh? Why? - Well, you can't fight a war with bombs like that.
- 为什么不能打   - 打仗第一天人就都死光了
- Why not? - Everyone would be dead the first day.
嗯
Mm.
噢
Oh!
他得到奖学金了
He's passed the scholarship!
他要去文法学校了
He's going to the grammar school!
嗯 希望不会太贵
Hmm. I hope he won't get too posh for us.
噢 厄尼斯特
Oh, Ernest.
好了 转过来 孩子 给妈妈看看
And there. There we are. Now turn around, sonny. Show Mummy.
噢 雷蒙德
Oh, Raymond.
你看起来好聪明
You do look smart.
等等
Oh, wait a minute.
脸蛋可不能脏 是吧
Can't have a dirty face, can we?
至少在学校里不能脏
Not at the grammar school.
的确 夫人
Quite so, madam.
- 语言 是吧    - 对
- Languages, eh? - Oh, yes.
他要学法语和拉丁语 还有数学
He has to do French and Latin. And maths.
哦 是不是算数
Oh, like arithmetic?
不只是算数 叫...代...
No, not just arithmetic. Um, it's called alge...
呃 代数
Um, alge-bra.
哦 体育呢
Oh. And sport?
- 他踢足球吗    - 不 他们玩橄榄球
- Does he do his football? - Oh, no. They play rugger.
艾瑟尔
Ethel!
不好意思 该走了
Oh, sorry, must go.
- 你不该和百纳提太太说这些的 亲爱的    - 为什么
- You shouldn't go on about it to Mrs Bennet, dear. - Why not?
她儿子没上学 现在是个砖匠
Well, her boy didn't get in anywhere. He's a bricklayer now.
- 我为我儿子感到骄傲还不行吗   - 当然可以
- I don't see why I shouldn't be proud of my own son. - Yeah? Well, OK.
- 嘿 嘿   - 妈 看
- Hey, hey! - Mum! Look!
- 怎么样    - 真棒 爸爸
- What do you reckon? - Smashing, Dad!
- 这是电车 儿子   - 希望你会开 厄尼斯特
- It's electric, son. - I hope you can keep control of it, Ernest.
- 我能上去兜兜风吗    - 别离那么近   - 太危险了
- Can I have a go on it? - Just you keep away from it. - Oh... - It's dangerous.
再见
ERNEST LAUGHS See you later.
Bye!
你好啊 厄恩
Hello, Ern.
你好 埃尔夫
Hello, Alf.
给
Ta.
- 怎么样    - 不怎么样
- How goes it, then? - Oh, not good.
我老婆 她脾气见长
My old lady, she's getting a bit much.
噢
Oh?
- 你是说吵架了?还是因为钱?    - 都不是 你懂的
- Rows, you mean? Money? - No, no, no. You know...
那件事
The other.
- 嗯    - 更年期
- Mm? - It's the change.
她更年期到了
She's on the change.
要求很多 你懂吧
Too demanding. Do you know what I mean?
我对付不了 太难了
I can't cope. It's too much for me.
所以 如果你喜欢 你懂的
So...if you ever fancy, you know...
- 就算你帮我个忙   - 呃
- You'd be doing me a favour. - Eh?
什么 你说
What? You mean, er...?
下周六我去看球赛
I'll be out next Saturday, football.
我老婆自己在家 所以
Fulham's at home. So...
你是说
You mean you...?
是啊 我说了 就算你帮我个忙
Yeah, like I say, you'd be doing me a favour.
天呐 不行 伙计 我不能做 不好意思 不行
Ah, blimey, no. No, mate. No, I couldn't. Sorry, no.
我的事还没干完呢
I've got a barrow to push.
别想多了
Er, no hard feelings.
要我也不会干
Nor me neither.
走了 埃尔夫
Ta-da, Alf.
- 再见 厄恩   - 埃尔夫
- See you, Ern. - Alf!
我认识一个胖胖的老警察
# I know a fat old policeman
总在我们的街道上
# He's always on our street
胖并快乐着的红脸男人
# A fat and jolly red-faced man
- 布瑞执太太   - 什么事
- Mrs Briggs? - Yes.
我是伯努利警探
Detective Sergeant Burnley, CID.
呃 怎么回事
Oh, no. Whatever is...?
你的儿子破窗潜入高尔夫俱乐部
Your son was apprehended breaking and entering the golf club
偷了很贵的台球杆
and stealing valuable billiard cues.
- 不    - 算他幸运
- No! - He's lucky.
这次只是给他一个警告
This time we're letting him off with a caution.
走吧 小子
In you go, sunshine.
下次就要进少管所了
Next time, it will be borstal.
不 不 不可能 他
No. No, it's not possible. He...
他上的可是文法学校
He goes to grammar school.
你个坏孩子
You wicked, wicked boy!
我真想杀了你
I could kill you!
- 对不起 妈妈  - 你怎么能干出这种事
- Sorry, Mum. - How could you?
少管所 少管所
Borstal. Borstal!
怎么了
Whatever's going on?
说啊
Well?
- 我看见你儿子从警车里出来的    - 是
- I see your boy came home in a police van. - Yes.
没错 就是从警车里出来的
Yes, he did. That's right.
他在协助警察调查
He's been helping the police with their investigations.
- 坐着囚车?   - 是
- In a Black Maria? - Yes.
他向警察报告了在丛林里看到的一起盗窃案
He reported some stolen property he found in the woods.
检察长说他是个聪明的孩子
The Chief Inspector said he was a very clever boy.
嗯
Hmm.
看 更多的工业废料
Look. More scrap Anderson.
刚好
Oh, fits perfect.
很快我们就拥有所有的煤了 即将实现国有化
We'll own all the coal soon. They're going to nationalise it.
我打赌还是会要钱
I bet we still have to pay for it.
当然会要 别想好事了
Of course we'll have to pay for it, you daft ha'p'orth.
那不还是不属于我们
So we won't own it then, will we?
这个 不完全是 但这意味着利润将会
Well, er, not exactly, but it means the profits will go
交给政府而不是跑到大老板的口袋里
to the government instead of lining the pockets of the bosses.
- 政府会把钱给我们吗   - 不会
- And then the government gives the money to us? - No.
这不结了 和原来一样 不是吗
So what's the difference, then?
老天 五万军嫂都要去美国 带着孩子
Cor. 50,000 GI brides going to America. Kiddies with them, too.
孩子 没结婚哪来的孩子
Children? But they're not married!
是没错 不过
Yeah, well.
可能是从枪里蹦出来的吧
I expect some of them jumped the gun a bit.
- 你知道他们是怎么说美国佬的吗    - 一拉就倒
You know what they say about the Yanks - one yank and they're down!
- 什么倒了   - 呃 这个 我也不知道 只是别人这样说
- What are down? - Er, well, I don't know. It's just a saying.
耶
Yaaay!
老天 将要建一千英里的高速公路
Blimey. There's going to be 1,000 miles of motorway.
极好的交通网
A terrific network.
那绿化带怎么办 还有乡下的美景
What about the green belt? All that lovely country?
我觉得应该会绕过去吧
Yeah, well, it will bypass it, I expect.
你不是说过已经有很多支路绕过去了嘛
I thought you said there were going to be lots of bypasses already.
我没说错啊 支路下面还会有支路
Yeah, well, so there are. It will bypass the bypasses, then.
那环形公路呢
And what about the ring roads?
可以绕过环行公路再绕过支路
Look, it will bypass the ring roads and bypass the bypasses.
- 绿化带也绕过去?    - 当然 绕过绿化带
- And bypass the green belt? - Yes, and bypass the green belt!
那好吧
That's all right, then.
只是觉得有点乱
Only it does seem a bit of a muddle.
他通过了
He's passed!
他通过了结业考试
He's passed the school certificate.
说他被准许...
It says he's matric...
准许入大学 之类的
Matriculated. Or something.
是好事吗
Is that good?
当然是
Well, of course it's good!
- 那是什么意思呢   - 我也不知道
- What does it mean? - I don't know what it means.
我们也不应该知道
Not our place to know.
- 早 布瑞执先生   - 早 天气真好
- Morning, Mr Briggs. - Lovely morning.
怎么了 亲爱的
Whatever's the matter, dear?
他说他想转去艺术学校
He says he wants to leave the grammar school and go to art school!
艺术学校
Art school?!
- 老天  - 我做了什么孽啊
- Oh, blimey. - Such a shame.
他本来能上个牛津或者剑桥的
He could've gone to Oxford and Cambridge
再找个好工作
and got a nice job in an office.
再不济也能当个领班 说不定还能当上经理
He could've been a foreman, or even maybe a manager.
学这个又不能赚大钱
There's no money in it.
根本挣不够花的
He'll never earn a living at it.
那里还有长发酗酒的...
That lot's all long hair, drink and...
- 裸体女人  - 噢 厄尼斯特
- nude women. - Oh, Ernest!
苏联今天宣布
- NEWSREADER: - 'It was confirmed today
已经引爆了自主研发的原子弹
'that Russia has exploded its first atomic bomb.
地点在哈萨克斯坦一个偏僻的地区
'The test took place in a remote area of Kazakhstan...'
苏联引爆原子弹了
Russia explosion, atomic bomb.
天呐 字幕
Oh, blimey. That's been and gawn and done it.
厄尼斯特 好好说话
Ernest, do speak properly.
爸 你工作回来 怎么不去浴室洗
Dad, when you come home from work, why don't you wash in the bathroom?
儿子 我身上太脏了你看
Blimey, son. I'm filthy, look.
我知道 可浴室不就是为这准备的吗
Yes, I know, but that's what the bathroom is for.
不行 不能去浴室洗 至少在英国我就不去
No, I couldn't wash in the bathroom. Not in this state.
可这是厨房 妈妈做饭的地方
But this is the kitchen, Dad. Mum cooks in it.
- 噢    - 真不行 儿子
- Ooh-ooh! - No, I couldn't, son.
- 不能在浴室洗    - 噢 爸爸
- Not in the bathroom. - Oh, Dad!
你好啊 儿子 在大学还好吗
Hello, dear. Had a good day at college?
他怎么了
Oh, what's up with him?
这叫青春期叛逆 亲爱的
They called it adolescence, dear.
他们就是不懂
They don't understand.
那自助洗衣店真是好东西
That launderette is a godsend.
洗完还能甩干 字幕
I did the whole blessed lot for 2/9 and it's all bone dry.
我也可以给水槽装个恒温器啊
I could get an electric thermostat for the tank.
夏季洗个热水澡 多时尚啊
Hot water in the summertime, all modern.
电动恒温器 电冰箱 电动送奶车
Electric thermostat, electric fridge, electric milk float.
我年迈的父母都不知道这些词是什么意思
My old mum and dad never knew the meaning of the word.
- 什么词    - 电
- What word, duck? - Electric!
家里一个挂电字的都没有
At home, there was nothing electric in the whole blessed house.
不也一样生活
We all grew up all right.
你们家不还是死了两个孩子 亲爱的
Two of you died as children, dear.
这和电有什么关系
What's that got to do with electric?
这就是进步 艾特 科学
Well, it's progress, Ette. Scientific.
科学的进步
It's scientific progress.
老天 这是什么
Blimey, what's this?
肉类供给降到两便士以下
Meat ration to be cut by tuppence.
这是自战争胜利以来的最低值
That's the lowest it's ever been and six years after the end of the war!
丘吉尔执政时肉才叫多
We had more meat under Mr Churchill.
好吧
Yeah, all right.
- 闪电战时期我们也有不少肉   - 是
- Middle of the Blitz we had more meat. - Yes!
- 英国之战    - 好啦
- Battle of Britain... - All right!
现在总怪不了希特勒了吧
You can't blame Hitler now.
别说了
No!
看看你自己的工人阶级政府
Just your Labour Government.
- 再见 妈   - 再见 儿子
- Bye, Mum! - Bye, dear.
你素描画完没
Have you finished your sketch?
看他们多般配啊
Just look at the pair of them.
她穿着黑色长袜 再看他的头发
Her in black stockings and just look at his hair!
他们可是艺术生 亲爱的
Well, they're art students, dear.
等他找到合适的工作就不会这样了
He'll grow out of it when he gets a proper job.
这样的头发到哪里去找正经工作
He'll never get a proper job with hair like that!
老天
Cor blimey.
这里有个普选候选人
There's a candidate here in the general election.
不只是个女人 年龄也只有26岁
Not only is she a woman, but she is 26.
我这年纪都能当她爸了
I'm old enough to be her father.
她还是个保守党员 这个世界是怎么了
AND she's a Tory. What is the world coming to?
我觉得是你的工人阶级追求人人平等
I thought your Labour believed in equal rights for everybody?
好吧 可...
Well, yeah, of course, but...blimey!
她已经达到结婚生子找工作的年龄了
She's old enough to be married, have a baby, go to work,
还能驾车 参军 在战场上开飞机
drive a car, be in the Army, fly a plane in the war.
是 可是...
Yeah, but...
老天 我倒想看看她能不能干我这个活
Blimey. I'd like to see her do my job.
人家才不想要你这个工作 人家要做国会议员
Oh, she doesn't want your job. She wants to be an MP.
- 人家受过教育    - 我就没受过吗
- She's educated. - And I'm not, I suppose?
你是没受过教育啊 是吧
Well, no, you're not educated, are you, dear?
我也没有
Nor am I.
我们根本就做不了国会议员
We couldn't be MPs.
- 噢    - 噢
- Aw! - Oh.
谁稀罕做国会议员啊 是吧
Who wants to be an MP anyway, eh?
奶酪限额降到一盎司了
Cheese ration cut to 1oz!
战后七年了   - 1盎司
Seven years after the war - 1oz.
都不够捕鼠器的诱饵
It's not enough for a mousetrap.
这就是你的保守党政府给你的
There's your Tory government for you, look.
你的丘吉尔奶酪
Your Mr Churchill's cheese.
你碰那奶酪之前最好洗过手了
I hope you washed your hands before touching that cheese.
这是我的服役通知
It's my call-up papers.
我要去皇家军团了
- ETHEL GASPS - I'm going in the Royal Corps of Signals.
我不准你去参加朝鲜战争
Well, don't you go and get sent to that Korean War.
仗都打完了  别大惊小怪了
Oh, that's all over, bar the shouting.
才不是 哈蒙德家的孩子 麦克尔
It isn't! Mrs Hammond's boy, Michael,
就是上周死在战场上的
was killed there only last week.
天呐 是吗
Blimey, was he?
他小时候还帮我送过奶
He used to help me on the milk round when he was a nipper.
他才19岁
He was just 19.
然后 要立正的时候
Then, when you come to attention...
立正
Attention!
必须要用力踢脚
You have to slam your boot down so hard
- 让血都从鞋里喷出来    - 可别 儿子
- the blood spurts through your lace holes. - Oh, don't, dear.
真的 妈
It's true, mum.
- 你们要进行空中跳伞吗    - 不
- Are you going to do parachute jumping, son? - No.
我是办公室里的制图员
I'm going to be a draughtsman in an office.
很好 不错 坐办公室
Oh, good. That's nice, an office.
谢天谢地你总算有了个合适的发型
And thank goodness you've had a proper haircut at last.
摩根太太家的儿子就是个办公室文员
Mrs Morgan's boy is going to be an officer.
- 是吗   - 你不想坐办公室吗
- Oh, yeah? - Don't you want to be an officer, dear?
不太想 妈 他们想要的是队长
Not likely, Mum. They want head boys, team captains,
在公共学校里表现好的
prefects, preferably public-school.
我只是语法学校里的中等人
I'm just a common little suburban grammar school oik.
但这身制服是真神气
Oh, but the uniform is so much nicer, dear.
再加上一双棕色的鞋
And you could wear nice brown shoes.
靴子  - 这太普通了
Boots - they're so common.
我们自己的电话
Our very own phone.
谁会相信呢
Who'd have believed it?
噢 亲爱的 你不在家的时候铃响了我该怎么办
Oh, dear, what shall I do if it rings when you're out?
那就接啊 傻瓜
Well, answer it, you daft ha'p'orth!
我不觉得我会喜欢这样
I don't think I like it.
啊
- PHONE RINGS - Argh!
快 快 快 厄尼斯特 电话要疯了
Oh, quick, quick, quick, Ernest! It's going off!
哼
Ahem!
你好
Hello?
什么事
Yes?
不是
No.
好吧 再见
Oh, right, goodbye.
打错了 亲爱的
Wrong number, dear.
噢 厄尼斯特
Oh, Ernest.
就像图画一样
It's just like the pictures.
还能看维克托·麦克拉格伦呢
Yes, we might get Victor McLagen.
- 他不是死了吗   - 他们还是能把他放出来
- He's dead. - They could still put him on.
我还是更喜欢泰阮派沃
Oh, I prefer Tyrone Power.
他更时尚一点
He's more modern.
你去接 厄尼斯特
You get it, Ernest.
见鬼
Oh, blessed thing!
我们儿子有了个摩托车真好
Fancy our little boy having a motor bike.
是辆小轮摩托车 艾特
It's a scooter, Ette.
拉姆布瑞塔 意大利品牌
Lambretta. They're Italian.
骑摩托车他还太年轻
He's far too young for motorbikes.
还有他又留起来长发了
And I see it's back to the long hair already.
他已经退伍了 亲爱的
Well, he's demobbed now, dear.
再见 妈 再见 爸
Cheerio, Mum! Cheerio, Dad!
- 再见 儿子   - 再见 儿子
- Bye, dear! - Bye, son!
他有三个证书了
He's got three certificates now.
可那都是些艺术证书
Yeah, but they're only art certificates.
靠这些又找不着工作
They won't get him a job.
这里还有个伦敦大学的呢
One is from London University.
- 我知道 可...    - 他能署上名
- Yeah, I know, but... - He can put letters after his name.
就像医生那样
Just like a doctor.
你好啊 苏西
Hello, Susie.
报上说同性恋将合法化
It says they're wanting to legalise homosexuality.
噢
Oh.
同性恋是什么
What's that?
你懂的
Well, you know.
就是两个男的...
It's like two blokes...
不和女人在一起
only instead of with a woman,
而是这两个男人在一起
it's sort of with one another, like.
你在胡扯些什么 厄尼斯特
I don't know what you're rambling on about, Ernest,
我觉得你也不懂
and I don't think you do either.
我去烧点水
I'll put the kettle on, shall I, duck?
泡杯茶
A nice cup of tea.
惊喜 亲爱的
Surprise, dear!
- 什么   - 嘿 快点
- What? - Hey, presto!
小心点 太阳会晒得我的毯子褪色的
Mind, the sun will fade my loose covers.
看
Look.
什么
What?
- 什么也没看见吗  - 没有
- Do you see anything? - No.
就没什么新的 以前没有的
Nothing new, different?
没有
No.
那辆绿车呢
That green car?
绿车怎么了
Well, what about it?
凯旋使者 昨天还没有的 字幕
Triumph Herald, it wasn't there yesterday.
外面不总是有别人的车停在那吗
There's always different cars stuck outside our house nowadays.
不 这辆很特别
Well, that one is special.
哪里特别了
What's special about it?
这是我们家的
It's ours!
别傻了 厄尼斯特
Oh, don't be daft, Ernest.
来吧 亲爱的 上车
Come on, dear. Get in.
噢
Oh, er...
我这样怎么上 我还围着围裙
I don't like to. I've still got my pinny on.
- 也没梳头   - 上来吧
- And I haven't done my hair. - Come on!
真是你的?
Is it really yours?
是我们的 亲爱的
Ours, darling.
关门 我们去转一圈
Shut the door, we'll go for a spin.
我还不知道你会开车
I didn't know you could drive a proper car.
雷蒙德的信
Letter from Raymond.
老天 男性人力劳动者每周
Crumbs! The average male manual worker earns
可以赚13.2英镑
£13, 2s and 11d a week. Blimey!
- 我一定低于平均水平   - 这对你又不适用
- I must be below average, then. - Oh, it doesn't apply to you, Ernest.
你又不是人力劳动者
You're not a manual worker.
噢 他要做一个老师
Oh, he's going to be a teacher.
很好 这才是个正经工作
Oh, good. That's a bit more regular.
- 是所艺术大学   - 那就更好了
- It's in a college of art. - That's better.
谢天谢地不是所简单的艺术学校
Thank God it's not just an art school.
- 业余的    - 业余的也好
- Part-time. - Well, part-time is no good.
有更多时间找老婆
That's more for women.
一周就上一天 看呐
One-day a week, look.
老天
Blimey.
一天的工钱就赶得上我一周的工钱
He gets almost as much for one day as I get for the whole bloody week.
厄尼斯特
Ernest!
噢 30号见
Oh, "See you on the 30th.
我会带着...珍...一起来
"I'll be bringing...Jean with me."
他们来了 艾特
Here they come, Ette.
嗨 妈 爸
Hello, Mum. Dad.
这是珍
This is Jean.
你好 珍
Hello, Jean.
你好
Hello.
Hello, dear.
看看你
Oh! Look at you.
这是梳子
Here's a comb.
妈 我一个月没见你了
Mum, I haven't seen you for a month.
我现在带着我未来的妻子来看你
I've just brought my future wife to meet you.
才不想要梳子
I do not want a comb!
那好吧
Right then.
呃 我去烧点水
JEAN GIGGLES I'll, um...put the kettle on.
对不起 妈
Sorry, Mum.
来坐下吧
Oh, come and sit down, dear.
很高兴能见到你
Lovely to see you.
你也是 琴
And you too, Jane.
是珍 妈
Jean, Mum.
我觉得你会喜欢...
I thought you'd like...
哦 谢谢 儿子
Oh, thank you, dear.
这是什么
Whatever is it?
- 是瓶酒 妈   - 酒
- It's a bottle of wine, Mum. - Wine!
- 噢 儿子 我不知道   - 有开瓶器吗
- Oh, dear. I don't know... - Got a corkscrew anywhere?
酒 噢
Wine! Oh, dear.
- 没事的 妈 不会炸    - 我不喜欢嘣的声音
- It's all right, Mum. It won't explode. - I don't like bangs.
哦
Oh!
- 再见 妈 再见 爸    - 再见 儿子
- Bye, Mum. Bye, Dad. - Cheerio, son.
希望你能换个好点的车
I do wish you'd get a nice car, dear.
面包车更便宜
A van is cheaper, Mum.
- 也不用上税   - 但买个轿车不是更好吗
- No purchase tax! - But a car is so much nicer.
再见
Bye!
- 那孩子不错 是吧    - 话不是很多
- She was a nice kid, wasn't she? - She didn't say much.
害羞而已 非常害羞
She's shy. Very shy.
像你一样 小甜心
Like you, sweetheart.
头发太长
Hair all over the shop.
- 太高  - 长得高又不是她能决定的
- Too tall. - She can't help that, dear.
- 腿长  - 别想了 厄尼斯特
- She's all legs. - Never mind her legs, Ernest.
她得烫发 他得剪个短发
She needs a perm and he needs a good haircut.
哦 不
Oh, no.
他说他们要在婚姻登记处结婚
He says they're going to get married in a registry office.
- 现在的年轻人都这样 艾特   - 真可怕
- Well, that's the modern way, Ette. - Oh, it's horrible.
是 可他们都没有什么宗教信仰
Yes, but neither of them is religious.
我不想让他信教
I don't want him to be religious,
我只是想让他在教堂结婚
I just want him to get married in a church!
那样更好
It's so much nicer.
你准备什么时候要个孩子
And when are you going to start a family, dear?
我也不知道 妈
Well, I don't know, really, Mum.
- 可能永远都不会要   - 为什么
- Probably not at all. - Goodness me, why ever not?
我想抱孙子
I want to be a granny.
这个 珍有点问题 妈
Well, Jean's got problems, Mum.
大脑的问题
Brain trouble.
- 大脑问题  - 对
- Brain trouble? - Yeah.
反正我是这样说的 就像开玩笑一样
Well, that's what I call it, as a sort of joke.
她进过疯人院
She goes in and out of the loony bin.
你是说
You mean she's...
- 她有神经病    - 对 可以这样说
- (WHISPERS) She's mental? - Yeah, well, that's one word for it.
准确地说是精神分裂症
The other word is schizophrenia.
哦
Oh, dear.
真可怜
Poor thing.
也就是说 我抱不成孙子了
So, I won't be a granny after all.
没事的 妈
Never mind, Mum.
真垃圾
What a dump.
垃圾
"Dump"?!
妈 这是政府设计的
Mum, the Government has designated this
有秀美自然风光的区域
an Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty.
这是官方的
An AONB - it's official.
我看还是垃圾
Well, I still say it's a dump.
南边的山丘挨着花园
The South Downs are at the end of the garden.
好吧 好吧
I give up, I give up.
儿子 这正是我梦想的地方
Son, it's the sort of place I always dreamed about.
我知道 爸
I know, Dad.
我知道
I know.
看起来他们在那儿很开心 除了犯病的时候
They seem very happy down there, despite the schizo business.
我想也是
Yes, I suppose so.
我还希望他会把脏衣服寄回来洗
I was hoping he'd send his washing home.
艾特 别傻了 他都结婚了
Oh, Et, don't be daft. He's married!
我知道
Yes, I know.
这是什么
What's that?
我的退休证书
My retirement certificate.
在皇家部队合作社奶场工作了37年
37 years' service with the Royal Arsenal Co-operative Society.
我可不想你把它挂在墙上
I'm not sure I want that on the front room wall.
不挂这挂哪 艾瑟尔
Well, that's where it's going, Ethel.
这是我的一小步
- ON RADIO: - 'It's one small step for man...
也是全人类的一大步
'..one giant leap for mankind.'
天
Cor blimey!
人上到月球上了
Man on the moon, Ette.
- 噢    人上月球
- Oh. - Man on the moon.
太神奇了 是吧
Fantastic, eh?
上月球干嘛
What's he doing there?
这个 就走了两步
Well, just walking about a bit.
然后呢
And then what?
应该就回来了吧
Come back, I suppose.
也许还会在那野餐一顿
Perhaps they'll have a picnic.
那也不错
That'd be nice.
我觉得一拿热水瓶倒水 水就飘走了
I think the tea would blow away when it came out of the thermos.
是因为风大吗
Why? Is it windy up there?
不 是因为重力
No, it's gravity, dear.
这样啊
Oh, I see.
看 他还要拿些月球上的砂砾带回来
Look. He's going to pick up some pebbles to take home.
就像沙滩上的小孩
Just like kiddies at the seaside.
关了吧 好吧
Turn it off, will you?
旅行快乐吗
Did you have a good journey, dear?
当然 还行 妈
Oh, yes. OK, Mum.
还好 还好
Fine, fine.
路上堵车了吗
Much traffic on the road?
A23路有点堵 是吧
Well, the A23 was a bit choked up, wasn't it?
一过萨顿 车就很少了
But after Sutton, it sort of thinned out a bit and, you know...
就会好点
got better.
给你梳子 儿子
Here's a comb, dear.
谢谢 妈
Thanks, Mum.
还记得我们以前经常推着婴儿车来这里吗
Remember we used to bring the pram up here?
现在坐在车里的成我了
It's me in the pram now.
战争之前这还会在包厢里泡上好的茶
They used to do nice teas in the balcony before the war.
服务员都戴着帽子 围着围裙
Waitresses in aprons and caps.
我们还没进去过 是吧 亲爱的
We never did go, did we, dear?
是 真好
Yes. It was lovely.
流氓把窗户都给打碎了
The yobbos smashed all the windows.
还不是因为你的工人阶级聚会
Well, that's your Labour Party for you.
- 布瑞执先生 布瑞执先生   - 怎么啦
- Mr Biggs! Mr Briggs! - What?
有没有电话 我得打急救电话
在楼下 医生 门厅
艾瑟尔
他们怎么都盯着我看
他们不是盯着你 妈 是电视
就放在你的床边
我不喜欢他们盯着我 我也不喜欢在慈善病房里
这不是慈善病房 妈
这是女士的名字
这是什么音乐
我能听见音乐
是卡罗尔 妈
在电视上 是圣诞节
圣诞树在这 看
噢 希望我能及时回家过圣诞节
- 什么时候是圣诞节   - 是昨天 妈
昨天你已经收到礼物了
看看你的贺卡
好漂亮的花
是 很漂亮
我真幸运
听着 孩子
刚刚那个老头是谁
噢 妈
那是我爸啊
你爸?
你认识的 厄尼斯特
你丈夫
我丈夫
是
我丈夫不是维克托·麦克拉格伦?
不是 妈
我还以为他死了
真漂亮
这花真漂亮 妈
是 真漂亮
我真幸运
儿子
是你吗
是
医院刚打来电话
- 好吧    - 她
我马上去
- 我也马上走   - 好
- 到时再见 - 再见 爸
冷静 儿子
冷静
为什么把她放在推车上
我也不知道
看 该死的纱布还在她脸上
牙都弯曲了
我看见了 儿子
我也不知道原因
我还是会准备两个人的位置 亲爱的
是不是很傻 苏西猫
水仙花真好 是吧
零售商告诉政府...
我冲杯可可茶 亲爱的
雇员要求...
晚安 苏西
啊
哦
噢
没事 苏西
我想该找急救队把这些东西都带走
这棵树是从一颗种子长起来的
艾瑟尔·布瑞执
厄尼斯特·布瑞执
1895-1971
1900-1971